# 大家好 今天我們來廣東這邊摘這個稔子哦
Hi everyone! Today we’re coming here to Guandong and pick some, some rose myrtle fruits.
# 帶了這個袋子來裝 裝來這個袋子就很不錯啦
We’re coming with this bag. It’s already not bad if we could fill up this bag.
# 剛好 兄弟姐妺都來廿
Just now, all my buddies, brothers and sisters are all here.
# 你看 正好給他(她)們一人發一個袋子
Look! Perfect! I can give everyone of them a bag.
# 不要跑 來
Don’t run away. Come here!
# 嗯 裝完這個袋子就可以啦
Um! Filling up this bag is all we need.
# 可以
Alright!
# 準備出發
Let's start, let's start!
# 你看 這種那麼多 他們都不要
Look! Here are so many. But they don’t want them.
# 這個紅的就可以用來泡酒 這種紅的
These reds ones can be used to make infused liquors, this red one.
# 這個黑的就可以直接 吃
And this black one can be eaten, right away.
# 你看 吃它的果肉 這個籽有點多哦
Look! We eat its pulp. This one has a bit too many seeds.
# 不要吃那麼多 吃多了會 會那個的
I need to refrain from eating too much. Otherwise, I'll, I'll, you know,
# 會上廁所上不出來
I’ll have difficulties on the toilet.
# 誒 這裡有
Eh! Here
# 一棵樹上好多個
There are a lot in this tree.
# 這上面有好幾個大的哦
There are some very big ones up there, you know.
# 看到好大
I see some very big ones.
# 哇 你看這裡有一個
Wa! Look, here’s a,
# 又大又黑
big and black one.
# 你看這裡有一個 又大又烏的
Look! Here’s another one, big and dark.
# 又大又黑
Big and black
# 哎呀 那麼多刺
Aya! Why is here so spiky.
# 你看這裡 好多啊這裡
Have a look here. Here are a lot.
# 看到沒有 這裡上面也有
See? There are more up there.
# 那麼多 沒人摘 可能我們來得早
There are so many, but nobody picks them. Perhaps we come early.
# 剛好 剛 剛好有個阿姨還在這裡摘
Just now, just, just now an auntie was picking here.
# 看到我們來了她就走了
But she went away once she saw us coming.
# 搞得我怪不好意思的
It makes me look very greedy.
# 等一下我摘一點送給阿姨吃
I’m gonna pick some for the auntie in a while.
# 你看這兩個像個小豬崽一樣 香豬崽一樣
Look! These two look like two piggies, little piggies.
# 這個紅了 這個沒壞
This one has turned red. It’s not rotten.
# 這裡 啊 不大不
Here. Ah! Isn’t it big?
# 你看這個 夠大吧
Have a look at this one. It’s big, isn’t it?
# 大到它肚子都爆子
It’s so big that it’s belly is even bursting out.
# 太甜了 胖的就是好吃
So sweet. The fat ones are always tasty.
# 肉多水多
Rich and juicy
# 才來 摘了半個小時才摘了那麼一丟丟
Just, I have just a tiny little bit here, after half an hour.
# 怎麼搞的
What happened?
# 換一個地方
Let me change to another place.
# 你看 這個時候還有金銀花哦
Look! Here are still honeysuckles in this season.
# 說明這風水好好啊
It’s an evidence of good fengshui.
# 哇 你看這個 又圓又大的 藏在這裡
Wa! Have a look at this one! Round and big! It’s hiding here.
# 這樣的就很漂亮的哦 這個
This one is really pretty, you know, this one.
# 你看
Look!
# 太浪費啦
What a waste!
# 你看 摘了一天就搞了那麼一點點
Look! I’ve picked just a tiny little bit here in a whole day
# 二兩都不到
It’s not even a hundred grams.
# 看他們摘多少 來來來來來來 集中在一起 看下有多少
Let me see how much they have. Here, here, here, here! Put them all together. Let’s see how much we have.
# 誒呀 可以可以 有半斤 哎呀 別摔破了
Eya! It’s not bad. It’s about a quarter of kilogram. Aya! Don’t smash it.
# 有兩三斤哦 可以哦
Not bad! It’s more than one kilogram,
# 三四斤都有
It's almost two kilograms here.
# 你看 是不是
Look! Right?
# 人多力量大 可以吧
Many hands make great power. Not bad, isn’t it?
# 拿回去泡酒 這個很好吃的哦
Let me take it back and make some infused liquors. It’s really tasty, you know.
# 這個不能吃多 吃的現在肚子痛了
Don’t eat too much. Otherwise I may have a funny stomach.
# 食太飽了
I've eaten too much.
# 可以 有三四斤
Not bad! It’s almost two kilograms here.
# 好啦 準備回去了
Alright! Let’s get ready to go back.
# 這裡還有養 養雞養鵝的哦
Here are also some, some chickens and geese as well.
# 這個圍欄 不安全啊 這裡
This fence, is not really safe here.
# 等下叫 叫她抓兩隻雞來燉
Let me, ask her to catch me a couple of chickens in a while. I'm gonna make a stew.
# 跟我們家的鵝一模一樣的
They look exactly the same as my goose.
# 這種肉質很好吃哦
Its meat is really tasty.
# 我都還沒吃過這種雞 花的
I’ve never tried this kind of chicken before. They're black and white.
# 我搞兩個來吃一下
Let me get a couple of them and have a try.
# 哇 還有一個白色的公雞喲 看到沒有
Wa! There’s also a white rooster. See?
# 把它抓回去
Let me catch it back home.
# 好像有蛋
It seems to have eggs.
# 沒蛋
No, it doesn’t.
# 你看 那還有個黑 黑雞公
Look! There’s a black, black rooster.
# 全黑的
It’s all black.
# 全場就一個黑的跟一個白的雞公
There’s only one black and one white rooster in the whole site.
# 其它全是母的
All others are hens.
# 你看 這個白的也是母的哦
Look! This white one is also a hen.
# 這個 這個叫蘆花雞
These are called Luhua Chickens.
# 我還沒吃過
I’ve never tried before.
# 啊 把它套起來 不要它跑啦
Ah! Put them into the bag. Don’t let them run away.
# 等下帶回去
I'm gonna take them back in a while.
# 剛好 人多 3個 一起吃手掉
Just so happen, many people today. Three chickens, eat them all.
# 剛剛拿出來
I’ve just taken them out.
# 曬了一下 沒太陽
Dry them under the sun. But the sun doesn’t shine.
# 老是沒太陽 不然會壞掉的
The sun is always hiding. They would be rotten, otherwise….
# 還不如直接就拿去
Why don’t we simply,
# 直接泡酒呢
make the infused liquors right away.
# 這個反正給兄弟喝的
After all, it’s just for my buddies.
# 隨便泡一下就可以了
There’s no need to take it too seriously.
# 兄弟又不會介意
He won’t care a bit.
# 兄弟很喜歡喝酒的哦
My buddy loves alcohol.
# 每次我來這裡都不醉不歸
He never leaves my place sober.
# 直接把它裝起來
Let me take them all right away.
# 裝起來放到下面去
Take them all down there,
# 搞點
and fetch some,
# 白酒來泡一下
some rice wine, then infuse them.
# 這個葉子要留下來
The leaves are to be kept.
# 看上去就比較青澀
So that it looks greener.
# 這個酒把它拆出來
Let me take out the rice wine.
# 先 先把稔子倒進去
Let me, let me put the myrtle fruits into the jar first.
# 這個 稔子
The, myrtle fruits…
# 哎呀 蠻多的哦 倒點酒下去
Aya! Quite a lot! Then pour the wine.
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 誒呀 你看 現在很漂亮啦
Eya! Look! It’s really pretty now!
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 搞點冰糖下去
Let me put some rick sugar.
# 多搞點 甜一點
More. Make it sweeter.
# 你看 這樣 再過半個月左右就可以喝啦 這個酒
Look! Then, it will be ready in a fortnight, the liquor.
# 把它蓋起來
Cover it up.
# 半個月之後就可以叫兄弟過來
In a fortnight, I can ask my buddy to come,
# 暢飲
and enjoy to his heart’s content.
# 你看 這個好漂亮啊這個
Look! It’s really pretty now.
# 泡在酒裡面悶著
Let it infuse and develop.
# 嗯 先放著來 下次叫兄弟過來喝
Um! Leave it here first, and ask my buddy to come next time.